♪ [music] ♪
- [Woman] I think it is impossible
to overestimate
the importance of Vidal Sassoon.
- [Man] He's probably one of the greatest,
if not the greatest hairdresser
that's ever lived.
- [Man] With raw talent and drive
and ambition and just sheer guts
and I will not give up.
He built something that rocked the world.
- [Woman] It was one man
with an amazing innovative idea
that has stood the test of time.
- [Host] Our next guest became famous
for creating The Shape,
The Five-point, The Bob,
and the many, many more.
- They were the styles which set him off
on the path to creating a multimillion
dollar international corporation.
-[Man] Well, he's an international
celebrity really who revolutionized
the way women of the world
looked on the outside
and how they view themselves
on the inside.
- [Man] Vidal was completely established
as the leading person
in hair in the world.
- [Man] Probably the biggest legacy
in modern hairdressing
is the name Vidal Sassoon.
- [Man] He's like, I supposed,
like a big deal in hairdressing.
- [Woman] I think if you went to Japan
and asked them [chuckles]
what hairdressers do you know?
They would say, "Vidal Sassoon."
They would know the name.
- [Man] It's like being a boxer
in the time of Muhammad Ali
or being a physicist
and working next to Einstein
because he was that good.
- [Woman] We think of Sassoon,
we also think liberation.
- [Man] He just seems to exude
this magic around him.
- [Man] If I was the Queen of England,
I would knight him.
- [Man] So much of Sassoon is a myth.
- [Man] I fought some great people
in my time,but for me, he is the person.
Yeah, he is the Messiah.
- [Vidal Sassoon] If you don't look good,
we don't look good.
♪ [rock music playing] ♪
-[Vidal Sassoon] You know I'm sitting here
reflecting really at 81.
Who would've dreamt that
sixty seven years ago,
at the age of fourteen, there I was
in the East End of London.
A "shampoo boy."
And then sitting here,
over sixty years later.
And I'm wondering,
"How did it all happen?"
How did so much adventure happen?
♪ [music playing] ♪
[Vidal Sassoon] Go back all those years,
you think
the excitement, the creativity,
the people you've met.
[people chatting]
- [Michael Gordon] So we're gonna go ahead
and start assembling the wall
because Vidal is coming to see it.
I've known Vidal about fifteen years
and I consider him a really good friend.
I've always been in the position when
I was the elder talking to other people.
So, having someone
who you respect immensely
and who has such an impact
on people's lives as a friend.
It's rather wonderful.
The more I got to know him,
I realized we had lot in common.
We were both hairdressers.
That's how we started off in London.
Both transitioned into having
product companies.
I realized that, actually,
nobody had really recorded
his achievements, his life.
So, I thought a book
was absolutely necessary.
I felt like it was really
important to capture.
He had an impact on the world
that no hairdresser has ever had.
He changed the way women looked.
♪ [music playing] ♪
This was the way books
used to be produced to magazines.
You put them on the floor or the wall.
You did a layout.
I think he'll really be moved to see this.
There were series of three
4-hour interviews.
Different places, different times.
The first place we interviewed him
was in his house in Beverly Hills.
[birds chirping] [water gushing]
- So, you were born 1928,
in Shepherds Bush?
- When I was, maybe, 2 1/2 to 3 ,
my mother was evicted.
You have to remember,
it was 1928 I was born.
So in '30, '31, the Depression was on.
My father left us. Had a young brother.
And unlike today,
where we're multi-cultural,
being Jewish, we stood out in those days.
We needed somewhere to live.
So, she appealed to the Jewish authorities
to take us into this orphanage here.
And I spent from five to eleven
in the orphanage,
and sang in the synagogue choir.
♪ [music] ♪
Hmmm
Seventy two years ago,
this is where I used to sit.
I was a choir boy.
The choir master,
he'd rap my knuckles on occasion.
[laughs]
'Cause, you know, we were kids
and we were naughty at times.
But they were charming services.
they were very warm, very gentle.
Right now, at this moment,
I don't know if I did then –
I was far too young.
But right now, I'm feeling all spiritual.
There's a sense of peace here
and it's a wonderful-shaped synagogue.
It hasn't changed.
I can't think of anything that's changed.
To give you just a few bars
of something that we used to sing,
we used to go Hallelujah, Hallelujah.
And the tune was
♪ [Hallelujah] ♪
[singing continues]
What I miss most is my mom.
They only allowed me to see her
once a month.
I ran away from the orphanage.
Went to my dad which is so much closer
than the East End where my mother lived.
He got me back to the orphanage
as quick as he could.
And I could see that
there was no caring or love.
You could tell that as he walked away,
when he passed me over to the authorities,
that he already had
something else on his mind.
He didn't even look at me.
And I think that moment, was when I lost
any love that I had for him.
Never saw him again.
- [Betty Sassoon] You see,
I had two beautiful sons.
And I'd always had that feeling
that I wanted my sons to grow up
to be very proud of their mother.
And think that helped me an awful lot.
- If there's anything you'd wish for me
in the future, what would it be?
- Oh, God, and this is the truth...
I wish happiness in your life
because you deserve it, son.
If anybody deserves it,
that's you because you've been…
to me...
Please, It’s the truth the best son
a mother could ever have.
And I think I am blessed by God
to have such a son.
- [Vidal] Her life was a painful one.
Mine was different. I knew nothing else.
The orphanage and then the war broke out.
- [Churchill] We can go on to the end.
We can fight in France.
We can fight on the seas and oceans.
- [Vidal] And then suddenly,
we were all picked-up.
All the kids of London
and sent to the country.
Where we lived with cows and sheep
for the next few years.
And of course very nice people
that took us in.
I came back to London at fourteen
and the war was still on.
And we were sleeping down the shelter
as everybody did.
And the Luftwaffe was rearranging
the streets of London every night.
The architecture was changing
at every moment.
-[Churchill] We shall defend our island
whatever the cost may be.
- [Vidal] I had a job as a glove cutter.
I was cutting the little snippets
that they would sew the gloves
together with.
It seemed I always had
a pair of shears in my hand.
Except for three months in London.
They needed messenger boys who had bikes
to take messages from
the city to the darks.
My mother had remarried Nathan G.,
Nathan Goldberg.
Great guy.
He got me a bike and I got the job.
The job was fascinating
because the streets were blocked
and buildings were down.
And I was riding this bike at fourteen,
really having fun.
[explosions]
You know you began to feel
like a war hero. [chuckles]
[crowd cheering]
- [Churchill] ...and in the streets,
we'll fight in the hills.
We shall never surrender.
My mother, she was always concerned,
saying, "You gotta learn a trade!"
She said, "Well, I've had a premonition."
"What's that mother?"
She said,
"You're going to be a hairdresser."
I said,
[whispers] "I'm going to be what?"
She said, "A hairdresser."
So she walked me by the hand.
Into a man called Adolph Cohen,
in White Chapel Road.
Now, White Chapel
is the heart of the ghetto.
And there was this wonderful
little man.
He couldn't have been more than five feet.
He asked for a hundred guinnes.
Now that was a a hundred pounds
and a hundred shillings in those days.
Which is an impossible figure.
My mother said, "We don't have
a hundred buttons."
I was kinda smiling because I was relieved
I wasn't going to be a hairdresser.
So I went to the door
and opened it for my mother
and ushered her through.
And I doffed the cap.
He followed us out.
He said "You seem to have rather
good manners, young man."
"Start Monday." He looked at my mom
and said, "Let's forget the fee."
So my apprenticeship cost nothing.
♪ [music] ♪
I was apprentice for two years
with Adolph.
Extraordinary man.
Pressed trousers every morning.
Clean nails. Clean Shoes.
Middle of a war --
how was that possible?
He was a disciplinarian!
And i think that had
an enormous effect on my sense of how
we should progress in our craft.
- [Joshua Calvin] They can't help even at
80 years of age to be mesmerized by him.
And he's such a well-read man.
He really does know a lot of things.
He has studied strongly. Self-educated.
I mean, let's say he started at fourteen,
at Adolph Cohen's, you know what I mean?
He is completely and utterly
probably one of the greatest examples,
particularly in our business
of a self-made man who's just made it big.
-You gotta remember I lived in times where
there was a lot of evil intent.
You know with fascism
and being a Jewish kid
and getting into all kinds of problems
in that area.
We'd seen the films of book of Auschwitz.
You know and in the bunker they found
sixty thousand pair of children shoes
but no children.
- Mosley came out of jail
with all the fascists
and they started putting on their
uniforms again.
They are doing exactly the same thing.
There's no way you could deal with them
on an intellectual level
or go out and speak your mind.
It was street fighting.
And a group of ex-servicemen
started an anti-fascist group,
and I swear within a year
the streets were cleaned of fascists.
- Youngsters like myself, we joined.
And we were given all the information.
Where they would be.
Where they've had their meetings.
We do some damage.
- [Announcer] And then the Mosley heist
moved into London
to hold a rally in Dalston.
Scene of many Mosley riots
in pre-war days.
- There was always this sense
of having to prove something to myself.
It was a very personal thing.
[people shouting and fighting]
Oh, I once came to work
bruised on one side.
Someone had hit me with a ring.
As I walked in, a client said,
"[whisper tone] Good God!
What happened to your face?"*
I said am nothing man,
I just tripped over a hip and...
-After the Holocaust,
you couldn't just sit at home
and allow these fags
be running around London screaming,
"We gotta get rid of the Yids."
They already got rid of six million.
- [Announcer] In May of 1948,
a new Jewish state, Israel,
was born in a bath of blood.
Jewish troops rounded out forces
from the city of Haifa
in the first of a series of battles
that were to reverberate through the years
- [Vidal] I found the concept of
going to Israel so fascinating.
That I put my name down and spent probably
one of the great years of my life.
I found myself there as a human being.
I mean I didn't think
of the great tragedy of the war.
I just thought as a kid
it was an adventure.
♪ [drumbeat] ♪
It became a state May '48.
I didn't get there till July.
♪ [whistling sound] ♪
We were in the Palmark
which was a 4-unit prison.
Tough times when comrades
were either killed or wounded.
It was a fascinating experience
being with those people
and sharing what I shared there.
Before I went through Israel,
I didn't know who I was.
As a Jew, you are a minority
in every European country.
It was the first time
that I could truly say
I found a sense of dignity
as a human being.
It's a very spiritual happening
being in the desert.
And the desert has a way
of making you bend to its will.
Looking up at the stars at night,
you often wonder
what are you gonna do with your life.
I mean, the only thing that I knew
how to do was hairdressing.
And at that time I wasn't very,
very good at that.
If I have to be in hairdressing, because
I have no other way of earning a living,
the craft would have to change
or I would. [laughing]
[people chatting]
- [Gordon] When he came back from Israel,
and went to study at the then
best hairdresser,
our famous hairdresser in London,
his name was Raymond,
known affectionately as "Teasy-Weasy."
He'd been there to fight,
and he came back to fight again.
He was fighting against
what the establishment was.
And despite the fact that
it was him against the world
he was determined to do it.
He wanted to change hairdressing.
Everything was changing.
Hair had to change.
He just happened to be the person
that was obsessed by it.
So, it was in fact his own war.
- [Announcer] No mention of art
would be complete without reference
to the age old study of beauty culture.
And the name that has become synonymous
with the grooming of beautiful women,
hairstylist Raymond.
- Well he was more than a character.
He had no shame.
He would do things
that was so outrageous. [chuckling]
Now, he once rode down the course of Ascot
during Ascot Week in a pink morning suit.
Of course it was all
over the newspapers. [laughing]
He did things like that.
- [Raymond] Well, I am wearing
what I call conservative Blue.
And it's a regency style.
I think men have been in mourning
since the death of Prince Albert.
Through the years of being drab
and they have been as what I would term,
the butterflies were coming out
of the chrysalis amongst the cabbages.
- Marvelous man!
And he had a small pair of scissors.
And he pruned the hair, he shaped it,
he angled the hair,
and he got some lovely, lovely work.
I mean he'd come in with a scissors,
the stars , the hair, the whole bit.
I mean when he walked into the salon,
nobody looked at anybody else.
It was just pure charisma
and what he could do
with the pair of scissors was tremendous.
He taught me how to cut hair.
Just a pair of scissors.
No thinning shears.
No razors.
Just a pair of scissors!
Then I had to put the geometry into it.
That was later.
-[Harold Leighton] There was this
change happening.
And Vidal was doing things
that they weren't doing.
Raymond was cutting sharp.
But I think after
Vidal came out of Raymond
and went to Bond Street,
he was cutting even sharper.
- Hair is nature's biggest compliment
and the treatment of this compliment
is in our hands.
As in haute couture,
the cut is the most important element
in deciding line.
Hair cutting simply means design.
And this feeling for design
must come from within.
You know when I started my own small...
It was a small business in Bond Street.
108 New Bond Street in 1954,
was 700 square feet,
and the first day
we had about three clients.
It was you know [chuckles]
we grew very, very slowly.
But I made up my mind then,
that if I was going to be in hairdressing,
long term, I wanted to change things.
I didn't have a picture
of what hair should be,
but I had a definite picture
of what hair shouldn't be.
- [Maurice Tidy] Great people know
who'd come in that time.
The type of work that
people know us for, did not exist.
At that time we were doing more,
I would term, more traditional
side of hairdressing.
You set hair.
You tease it.
And put it in place.
And if it didn't stay for a week
you were in big trouble.
- [Lawrence Taylor] In the '54,
he was really starting to experiment
and look for where
his direction was going.
Some days, if the cut wasn't going right,
he'd throw the brush and comb
up in the air,
and leave the building
and we wouldn't see him again.
He was crazy, actually.
He was crazy, oh, he was crazy
when clients would touch their hair.
Whether they would touch it and say,
"Oh that looks nice."
But before they could get that
"looks nice out,"
Vidal would smash among the knuckles
with a comb.
So when a client got a rap
on the knuckles.
It was a rap on the knuckles.
-[Vidal] I was a naughty boy.
When i was frustrated about the work.
I actually did once throw my scissors
in the air and got stuck in the ceiling.
So, I took it as as omen
and went to Paris for two weeks.
But then came back.
But that's the only time I did that.
Other times, I'd throw the brush down
and go for a walk,
come back half an hour later
having given myself a good talking to.
And for me being above it
was being the best I could
on what I did.
And when it wasn't going well,
it was frustrating.
There were times at the end of the day,
when it wasn't a good day.
And I have no one to turn to
because we were trying to do something
totally different.
And I'd sit at the end of the day
very often listening to Miles Davis,
Kind of Blue or Marvelous Eight.
♪ [music] ♪
And sitting alone and ponder,
"How do you change something?"
But when you found something,
Suddenly, I don't know,
you lit up like a beacon
*you kinda -- there was a sense of...
This is new.
This is, this is gonna be special.
We were drawing the attention of people
that wanted to see, "Who is this guy?"
who refuses the backcomb.
And he wouldn't even do
what we asked him to do.
He tells you he's gonna do
what he thinks is good for you.
I didn't want to do hairdressing
the way it was done.
I just didn't want to do it.
I wouldn't.
♪ [music] ♪
If I couldn't change things
from hairdressing
to what I consider would be
a different form of art.
You see, hairdressing was an art form.
I mean, people like Alexander or Raymond,
they do superb deal wonderful work.
Those wonderful work
being done in London.
But, when I look at the architecture.
The structure of buildings.
They were going out worldwide.
And you saw a whole different look
in shape.
My sense for hairdressing
definitely needed to be changing.
♪ [music] ♪
Great architects was were I came from.
That was my inspiration.
The Bauhaus Architecture.
♪ [music] ♪
For me, hair, meant geometry,
angles of bone structures.
Cutting uneven shapes,
as long as it suited that face
and that bone structure.
♪ [music] ♪
So, it meant in essence,
getting away from the old fashion.
I say old-fashioned but very pretty.
I can't knock it.
It was beautiful hairdressing.
But it wasn't for me.
I wanted to eliminate the superfluous
and get down to the basic angles
of cut and shape.
♪ [music] ♪
It took nine years, '54 to '63.
It took nine years.
And they were probably
the most exciting nine years
of my creative life.
And I don't know how we got there.
Because there were many
lonely,down times,
when I'd sit in my flat and think
"I'm wasting my time."
-Elaine, his first wife, ran the desk and
was absolutely incredible and wonderful.
- Elaine, what a darling.
I was 28, she was 21.
It was the most important thing
in my life, in the sense.
Not the salon itself, the work.
It was the most important thing
in my life.
I was so busy with my work, that she
fell in love with the ski instructor
because I used to water ski.
And in the final analysis,
I thought it was much better
for two people to be happy
than three unhappy.
- [Gordon] He recreated himself.
He wanted to be a success.
He tried to get into Raymond a few times.
He walked in with his cockney accent.
And the imperial-looking receptionist
looked down at him and said,
"Son, you'd better go and learn
how to speak English first."
I mean, can you imagine
what it feels like to be turned away
because you cannot speak
your language properly?
I meant, you take that as a slap
in your face or as he did,
"Oh! I see.
I need to go and learn English."
So, he did.
- [Christopher Brooker] He was
an ordinary person
coming from very humble beginnings.
- [Woman] But you've cut off other things,
you have no cockney accent.
You wouldn't know from just looking at you
the way you dress, the friends you have,
that you ever came from L.A.
or you went there.
Did you work at it?
- [Vidal] There was a lot of work
to be done.
You leave school at fourteen.
Hello darling! You talking a bit like that
then, you know, you got all that
cockney stuff going
bit under the arm and all.
I am trying to get a job
with a cockney accent when I was a kid.
Nobody would employ me in Mayfair
and people used to say,
"Well, take elocution classes."
- Did you?
- Of course I did.
I went to Iris Warrren and she said,
"I work with actors
not hairdressers." [chuckle]
I said, "Alright, thank you."
She said, "No, no! Be at The Old Vic.
On Thursday, at two o'clock,
I turned up at The Old Vic.
She said, "Up on the stage"
"You see something there
that you can read on the podium?
I said, "Yes."
She said, "Enunciate."
Just the one word.
And there was something for me to read.
So, I enunciated.
And she said, "My God! It's bloody awful!
But I think I can do something with you."
So, for three years, when I was in town,
wasn't out doing shows,
I was going to Iris Warren.
She was working on the vowels.
And it does work, it does help.
It wasn't just the production of voice.
It was when to keep it low.
When to bring the audience in
and when to modulate your audio.
It was totally fascinating.
*It gave me the sense anyway
that I could speak to a crowd of people
and bring them in to what I was saying,
and have them understand.
And it proved incredibly valuable.
Had I gone to college,
I would have definitely been an Architect.
That would have been my dream,
to be an Architect.
Nineteen fifty-four,
we worked in a very small salon.
I was 26 then, and after two years,
became far too small.
It was a work-up
on the third floor virtually.
Then we moved to a much larger salon
in Bond Street posh end as they say.
First, we did a white salon
with a black boutique.
And then later, we turned the whole salon
into brown,
with just steel bars in the front.
It looked like a hairdressing salon.
It looked like a modern art gallery.
♪ [music] ♪
As we were changing everything,
there's change of salons as well.
So we changed the look of the salon.
- There was his fabulous photographs on
the wall as a collection of photographs.
The tables were very modern.
Everything was modern.
It was open.
You could see from the street
into the salon.
Now in those days, that was very unusual.
That people would actually be seen
getting their hair done
was a revolution.
- And people were walking around
with a sort of a [snapping fingers] buzz.
A click.
And, it sort of created
a soar of excitement.
- And there was a mezzanine floor
with all these women standing.
Hundreds of people in there.
It was very difficult even to get
to the receptionist
because it was just
so many people in the shop.
- There was a hush in the salon.
You hear the snapping of scissors.
You hear -- not much chat going on.
It wasn't like a heavy-gossipy place.
It was like quite intense.
-In this classy salon,
boys fresh from Stretton in the suburbs,
give their long-suffering customers
not what they want
but what Vidal Sassoon
believes they should have.
- You're not gonna cut my hair forward,
are you?
- [Vidal] Well, Lynda, when you came in,
I noticed that your hair was combed back.
- Yes, I like it combed back,
it's more flattering.
I'd rather it went back from there.
- Why do you want it combed back?
Give me one good reason.
- Well, it gives me height up there.
- So, all your worrying
about its height really.
- Yes.
- Not the fact that it goes
back or forward but height.
- It's what I've always had
it going back there.
- Ahh, we don't go what you've always had.
Listen to me one moment.
When you came in, because your hair
was combed back and grows forward
what you were getting here was a part,
but it was an unintentional part.
My feeling is that if your hair
is shaped the way it grows.
Listen, [chuckling]
if it's shaped the way it grows
and you have your height put into it
right across the hair,
you are gonna get a much more defined
and better shape.
You'll get all the height you need
and the shape of the head
will actually look better.
Try this way.
- Alright.
- What I need to do is cut it in a way.
But if you feel you still don't like it,
come back.
You can take it back.
- Vidal walked into the salon
and will be working
and there will be quite a buzz going on
but, he'd walk in and suddenly
there would be a bit of a hush until
he goes, "First client in the chair."
And his assistant was there
with his scissors and his combs
and then the tempo would
pick back up again
as he got going.
Alright, he's in.
He's settled.
He's crimping. We're in.
We're on again.
- [Client] Do you always insist
on giving people what you think is right
rather than what they ask for?
- Well, the work is technical,
but on the other hand
it is instinctive as well.
And if your instincts tell you that
what you're doing is wrong,
then you mustn't do it because
you're gonna make a bad job of it.
I think that makes sense in anything.
- [Client] It takes a long time to grow
out, surely if somebody complains
you're really in trouble.
- Uhmm, that's true, I mean, I think that
people who are trying
to do something a little different
more often go out on a limb.
If you're not trying to be safe
all the time, on the other hand,
you're going to be more progressive
and get more done.
I think it works that way.
- His creativity was at epic level.
It was just -- everything he did,
every section he thought
he was like a piece of art in motion.
- It's like listening to music
or you know having a great meal.
You know, you know, or seeing Vidal work.
There was something magic about
how Vidal was because he would dance.
- Most people when they cut hair,
they cut with this comb and scissors.
Vidal cut with his whole body.
- He would move.
He would sweat, he would make faces.
He would cut hair with snip, snip, snip!
- Vidal was in his patent leather
slippers, with his tight trousers.
He was dancing around the chair.
He was pulling faces.
- [Client] Do you have one particular
kind of style that you put every year
or is it just anything that suits anybody?
- Well, that's a difficult one to answer.
I think each year we try
to bring out something.
We try to innovate something
a little different.
- [Client] Yup, this is alright for
somebody my age or older.
But what happens to someone
20 years older?
It can't work for everyone.
[scissors snipping]
- The VMA's however -- every line,
whether it be hair or clothes.
[scissors snipping]
A client would take something from it.
There is always something
that they can take from it.
Even if they don't have the actual right.
- [Client] There must be an awful lot of
turned bad from here in that case.
- Am gonna let you stew in that one
am not gonna answer it. [laughing]
- [Client] I hope you're not snipping
too much off in revenge.
- Vidal made everybody nervous,
especially me.
I would feel instantly sweat
coming all over me.
And you know, your hands
would start shaking.
- We were told never
to call the clients "madame."
Always to call the clients "madam."
We were told to open the door
for the client.
We were told to call the taxi
We were told to get the lunch
for the client.
- He would not tolerate any, anything
that wasn't up to scratch.
If you did look the part, that's it, you
just-- you went-- you're out of the door.
If you hadn't cleaned your shoes that day,
boy! you know that's it, you are out
you weren't there,
you're just out the door.
- And there I was doing this haircut
and I'm pulling the hair out,
and I could feel him behind.
And not only do I feel him behind, but
I could hear him going snip, snip, snip.
As I was cutting he was going snip,
snip, snip. Snip, snip, snip.
And it was freaking me out.
- I remember one time, he sent me home
because my shoes were not polished.
He's just you know, he was very strict.
Every time I assisted him,
if I got distracted for a second
he would take his comb,
he would snap my hand
and said, "put attention."
- Well, for Vidal to check your haircut
was the end of life.
Because you knew, he was gonna find
something wrong with it.
Because nobody could do a haircut
to the perfection of Vidal.
So he would pick the hair up
[mocking Vidal].
And he'd go over this haircut, and
he'll say, "You've gotta get it right,"
and you've gotta pull that hair.
You've gotta put tension on the hair."
"Move your body. Cut it again."
- But you know when -- the thing is,
you knew when he was tough
when his voice is lowered.
He has this kind of whispering thing.
And it's a, "I don't think
you are right for here."
"You don't seem to understand it."
*So i suggest you go that way
and don't come back again."
But the minute that voice is lowered,
you know that was it.
- I knew we were getting there.
We weren't there,
but we were getting there.
I got a call from the
film production company.
Would I cut Nancy Kwan's hair.
♪ [music] ♪
And she just made a great film
with William Holden,
which was a big success.
She came in, gorgeous girl.
With four feet of hair down her back.
Her producer, her manager --
it was a whole team.
We took over the 2nd floor.
And I started to carve
into this head of hair.
And I saw by bringing
the back up slightly.
And keeping the length of the sides.
Not four feet.
But keeping length of the sides,
You get a great angle from the side
and she could shake it.
It would fall in.
Well, she was petrified.
She played chess with her manager
while all this was -- she couldn't look.
And I am seeing something.
And I said to my assistant, I said,
"Would you please get Terry Stone
over on the phone.
So Terry gets on the line.
Terry, I think we got something.
I'm working on Nancy Kwan now.
I'd like to bring her in this evening.
Can we work tonight?
He said, "Yes."
And the architectural sense
of what we were doing,
making a statement.
That's what matters.
Making a statement.
And got it off perfectly.
I mean that picture went to
American Vogue, to English Vogue,
to Italian Vogue.
It went first to all the Vogue's
then the papers picked it up.
I knew then, we are on to something.
- [man talking] I think the five-point,
It was part of the most famous haircut,
the most photographed.
The model in the five-point haircut
is Grace Coddington,
who went on to become Creative Director
at American Vogue,
and has been for a long time.
- [Grace] At that time, I had hair
a little bit longer than it is now.
Vidal was like, super smooth
and he had this gentle voice
and-uhm-he sort of sat me down.
And I guess he liked my hair
because he started cutting it and...
Where there great joy for a moment.
Especially, you know when the
five-point cut really worked.
And Clare Rendlesham gave it
a whole middle of quaint in two- ages.
And -- those exciting moments but the lead
up to it could be terribly frustrating.
Five-point cut for me was the epitome
of nine years of work that led up to it.
It was the last cut of geometry
that in essence covered the whole head
because you have to create the points,
here, depending on bone structure
where it was on the individual character
working on
and you send the point in the back
of the head and the two --
so that you actually have five points.
- Then I remember feeling the back and
feeling that you know it's cut right out
into -- into the hairline.
That was pretty revolutionary.
And it's kinda finished and he said
"Stand up, okay. Shake it.
and it was shhhh...you know,
and it was extraordinary.
- The thing about it was,
that the hair itself when it was brushed
anyway or you put your fingers
through it had to fall back perfectly.
Five-point cut was the essential
geometric shape.
♪ [music] ♪
He gave me the opportunity.
I mean, he put me there.
You know, that was him
and Mary Quant, too.
And they're kinda of synonymous really
with that moment.
You know I think the mini-skirt
is very connected
to Vidal and how he saw her.
- [Gordon] Mary Quant was credited with
creating the mini-skirt.
And his prolific outpouring of designs.
The interesting about Mary and Vidal
was that they collaborated.
She was walking down Bond Street and
she happen to look at her little window
and there was a photograph
in it of a hairstyle
and she loved it.
She went upstairs with her husband,
she said,
"I knew then and there
that i wanted him to cut my hair."
- You came in 1957 with Alexander.
Well,he was one of the great characters
of Funky Green.
He was marvelous.
- [Mary] He was.
- He really was a personality.
Superb.
And I don't know why,
it wasn't a custom of mine
but the first time I cut your hair
and I cut your ear. [laughing]
- And you had all your staff watching.
[both laughing]
- And blood was...
- The cut was all over.
- It was [gushing sound],
blood flying everywhere.
- And you were pretending...
- That nothing happened [laughing].
- ...that you hadn't noticed.
you were cutting away.
- I loved it.
- And Alexander said,
"Oh, do you charge extra for that?"
[laughing hard]
- The Times Newspaper wrote an article
with nine pictures of how Mary Quant
changed the '60s.
And I was fortunate enough to be there
to -- shall I say hope you do it, Mary.
- And Vidal Sassoon
changed hair forever. [laughing]
- [Mary] You put top on it.
♪ [music] ♪
- [Vidal] I can remember,
It wasn't just your atelier in Kings Road
the whole Kings Road was your atelier.
Do you remember it one time?
- [Mary] The kings Road was the catwalk.
- [Vidal] Oh! It was wonderful.
-[Mary] I had a piece of Time Magazine
on one side, Elle Magazine on the other.
And the photographers were actually
photographing each other across the road.
- [Vidal] Almost yeah.
- [Mary] With all the excitement, yeah.
- But in the '60s,
there was a mingling.
- [Mary] Yes.
- [Vidal] It wasn't just the film celeb.
Everybody had come to London
to be creative.
Whether they were actors, photographers.
-[Mary] That's right.
-[Vidal] You know whatever --
the brightest.
So London became
that marvelous melting pot.
-[Mary] Of everything for everyone.
- [Announcer] A young woman who's
changed the dress ideas.
The outlook on clothes
of the new generations
throughout the Western world,
Mary Quant.
The artist in her sensed
that millions of young girls
longed for something entirely different.
Being one of them, so did she.
- Everything changed.
- The power.
- The meritocracy was youth.
- Yeah.
-[Vidal] Youth, creativity, excitement.
- [Mary] They called it, "youth-quake."
- [Vidal] Yeah.
[chuckling]
- And you were their head quake.
- Quakey. [laughing]
♪ [rock music playing] ♪
- We were telling the public,
you haven't had this before.
It's new, try it.
- It was a bit difficult if I remember
because in those days,
everybody had a great deal with hair.
I mean all the models did.
And we have a terrible job persuading
these top earning girls.
I mean the best ones that it was worth
having all that beautiful hair cut off
into this extraordinary five-point shape.
By three o'clock in the morning,
they were unable to work
for anybody else ever.
[guest and audience laughing]
- I love this picture.
- Let's not close that.
- No, let's not close.
I love it.
- Peggy Moffitt.
- Yeah.
- And she was the hell of a girl,
wasn't she?
- Peggy could, uhm -- and did
act out every hair look.
- [chuckles] Yes.
- And if she was wearing your clothes,
it would even be more --
you wouldn't see her for 10 minutes
because she'd be in the mirror
doing all kinds of strange moves.
Dance moves.
- New moves. New moves for a new dress.
- And she gets in front of the camera...
Wow!
- Yes, yes.
- It was magic.
- Yes.
♪ [music] ♪
- You see nobody could cut hair like that.
I mean, you cut hair as we cut cloth.
You cut it on the straight.
You all said, cut it on the cross.
And the most exciting of course
a cut on the cross.
And you cut hair across.
I think that's how you arrived
at an amazing diamond haircut.
-[Prof. Cox] The name Sassoon is important
because we associate it
with an incredible change in culture
that was happening in the early 1960s.
When you saw somebody dressed
in a Quant outfit with a fantastic
five-point Sassoon haircut,
you do not know if they were Countess.
You don't know if they were, you know --
someone who worked in the shop.
That was really a dramatically changed
how people thought about Britain.
You know, it was no longer this
high-bounce, kinda class-oriented society.
And I think also what really changed
how women thought about themselves
because women were not only liberated
kinda sexually and socially
you know, in the 1960s.
They were also liberated
through their clothes
and very particularly to their haircuts.
They were no longer having to go
to the salon every week
to have their hair permed and set
and tweaked and back-combed.
They could go into, you know,
a wonderful Sassoon salon
that was full of incredible energy.
And they could have a hair cut
that they could go out,
wash once a week, twice a week.
You know, do it all at home.
And it will look fantastic.
- And then, of course on Saturday,
he would be off the jobs in the afternoon.
But he would still be on the business.
But he used to physically work,
absolutely his hardest everybody did
on a clientele four days a week
in those years.
♪ [music] ♪
- Better than the psychiatrist couch.
I come here to Chelsea
on a Saturday afternoon
after working with the ladies all week
was exactly what I needed.
I remember as a kid, I've been coming
for 65 years when I was fourteen.
The first time I came to Chelsea
and I was standing way back there
because in those days there weren't seats.
It was just a few
on this side of the ground.
As we -- the business grew a little,
I got my first season ticket.
You'll never guess what it cost --
eight pounds!
It was right at the end.
Football in the sense is a cross
between chess and ballet.
The players have to have
that marvelous finesse.
As they're playing.
As they're moving.
Also, the team spirit,
'coz that's what we tried to do in here.
Build a great team that eventually
went international
and did exciting things.
We start talking about teams.
Think of a football team.
We had a Manager called Zola.
He was the engine
and he brought the standard
of everybody else's play up.
That's all I was, I was the engine.
I was the engine that created a team
that eventually -- it's a superb work.
That when I went to New York
they didn't miss me.
It is such good work.
They didn't need me
and I think that's the essence
of always creating around you talent.
I had such an extraordinary team.
You know, there's Roger Thompson,
there was Christopher Brooker.
There was Joshua Galvin...ahh
Trevor Sorbie, Leonard.
They all made big names
for themselves anyway.
This is my team.
The whole essence.
The excitement of our creativity.
And I say "our" because
it's always teamwork.
Yes, I led it.
But it was our excitement,
our creativity was the changes.
Those marvelous changes.
We were, we we're on cloud nine.
- You started your, your school. So?
- Well I...
- Which I thought was the most
generous thing I'd ever heard of.
- No. It was...
- [Mary] And you taught them how to cut.
- Well, that was the intelligent thing.
Look, if you just do something, Mary.
And you're a five-year wonder
and goodbye, you're gone.
But if people feel its worthwhile,
not only they copy,
but they want to learn how to do it.
- Yeah.
-So, then, you open an academy.
And then they come in
from many different countries.
- Uhum.
- And you learn --
- And particularly Japan and the Far East.
- But also from all over Europe, Africa.
- Everywhere.
- Yeah, from everywhere.
And suddenly you are opening
more and more academies
and you're teaching your methods
and to me that was it was all about.
If someone would say,
"What was the number one thing
in essence that you left behind?"
It was the teaching of others so they
could take your work and take it further.
- Suddenly, the word was spreading out
there amongst the hairdressers
that this was revolutionary.
- [Vidal] The energy emanating
from that place was quite extraordinary
and that led to the sense of
being international.
Once we opened up the school
and we had all these people
coming in from Japan, Germany,
you name it.
And then of course New York happened.
And, ahh -- I came to America. [chuckles]
♪ [country song playing] ♪
- [Vidal] New York, Pierre Hotel.
Primpers were coming from everywhere,
different countries.
And I felt these three girls,
and worked on them day before,
and cut the hair and cut the shapes
as I wanted them.
Sunday, the Press turned up.
The Press don't turn up on Sunday.
The Press turned up.
And they were taking pictures like crazy.
The following day, there were
five newspapers in New York,
we hit the front page
of their beauty page.
It was wild.
And suddenly, there we were in New York,
in New York City
where a great salon on Madison Avenue.
[beeping sound]
♪ [rock music playing] ♪
Lived in New York for 10 years.
Lovely, traveled with just a briefcase
'cause we had a little pad in London.
A little apartment
and a little one in New York.
So, I was going back and forth.
My life at the moment is so much
on the move which I find very exciting.
After I've been, say, two months in London
working, I get the urge to see
how we're doing in New York and
I go over there and do some more work.
So, if you're asking me,
would I like to live in pedicured lane?
I wouldn't particularly like to live
in any one place
for too long at this point.
-What happened in America was
we were the Beatles.
We were the hairdressing Beatles
on Madison Avenue.
-And they took this team over to New York
which was revolutionary
in New York at that time.
Because -- God bless them -- you know,
the Americans were a little behind
with their hairdressing styles.
But they were around the world.
They haven't caught up yet.
And that team, all looking like Beatles
and mini-skirts on the girls up to here
that's what's really, you know,
it's the word on the street.
It just happened that
around about the '60s.
Most of our guys were heterosexual
and I have to have a staff meetings
because, I said, "Listen fellows,
we're professionals!"
You've got to stop
sleeping with the clients!"
I mean, you've got to remember,
it was the days of
extraordinary sexual freedom
I mean, penicillin cured everything.
- [Grace] It was the wildest salon,
all the hairdressers were really --
they were all pretty hot
kind of like the movie Shampoo,
you know.
It was all hands everywhere.
Vidal had beautiful girlfriends always,
I remember.
and they always had, of course,
gorgeous hair.
- It was a marvelous time.
- Vidal had become a major celebrity.
He was on talk shows.
He did Mike Douglas.
He was on The Today Show.
He was on the Tonight Show.
He was the mystery guest on
What's My Line.
- Right now
let's meet our first contestant.
Will you enter and sign in, please.
Mr. X.
And we let the audience in the theater
and the audience at home know exactly
what your name is and what your line is.
[audience clapping]
- Do you represent men's fashion
in England?
- Do you have -- do you have anything
to do with handling fabrics?
- Mr. X, do you have anything
to do with hair?
- Yeah. [chuckles]
- [Woman] Oh! It's Sassoon!
- Yeah, who's line!
[laughing] [audience clapping]
- Actually I came here this time
not particularly to work
but to marry an American girl.
- Ahhhh.
- We moved probably this summer of '68.
We were going back and forth
for some time.
But this was about a year-and-a-half
after we got married
that we moved to New York.
And then Catya, our daughter,
was born in 1968.
All the kids were born in New York.
♪ [music] ♪
We lived in a, in a little apartment.
So it was an interesting time.
Vidal was a -- he was a good dad.
And he used to come home
in the middle of the day
and he'd picked up one of the kids
and take them on his shoulders
to Central Park, you know,
and he was very much involved
in being a father.
- I was in New York till I was 3 years old
and he used to take
me and my older sister out
and throw me on his shoulders
and ran around the city.
It was one of my first memories.
- Handsome looking guy, slim
health fanatic, a keep-fit superhero.
- [Woman] A hairdressers life is not
all frills and perfumes and half a grand
slipped into a tight back pocket.
In Vidal Sassoon's world,
the next best thing
to a well cut head is a well-built body.
- Always took time out
to look after his health, always.
- [Vidal] If your body is not right,
your mind will react.
If your mind isn't right,
your body is gonna react.
See, you have to work essentially
on developing the mind if you can.
And the other thing I regret not having is
four years of a great college to expand
the mind's that would take
in so much more.
But physically, I was always swimming.
I was--make sure I work out.
Took massage and it worked for me
because I could work 14 hours a day.
♪ [music] ♪ [water splashing]
I think in any industry or craft, art,
you need to spend more time at it
if you want to become good
than the average.
It's not a nine till five thing,
it could be a 14-hour a day.
By the time you finish with your models
and your hobby
and then you go to work the following day.
I was very careful with the food.
I exercise. Always have.
It is important to stretch the back out.
As much as far as you can.
Stretch it out,
stretch it out, stretch it out.
It's a wonderful feeling,
is to have the agility
not quite of your youth obviously.
But nevertheless, have the agility
to move like a younger person.
And I love this.
I think this stretching is marvelous.
I started doing Pilates
about 25 years ago,
and some of the stretches
come from Pilates.
The whole thing about this is fascinating
which is because in California now,
the Orthopedic Hospital are taking it to
work with children,
using this to work with children
who have muscular diseases.
So it's remedial, dances.
It's very effective for everybody.
- Oh! I can't wait for you to demonstrate.
-Here we go.
♪ [music playing] ♪
- Like this?
- Yeah.
- I like that.
- Now take the spring.
- Now what were you looking at.
- The ceiling.
There you go.
Now come back.
Now, you should be sitting
further forward.
Here we go.
Now, lie back.
Now, bring yourself up
and bring your legs up.
Now bring your body up.
- Isn't there an easier way
to take a work out?
[audience laughing]
- When I was overtired
as one would become,
I go to places like Great Shot Hole
and hang out there for 10 days
and do the full treatment.
I met some incredible characters there
and who was there but Gore Vidal's.
Monday morning your down there
for your treatment at eight o'clock.
and they said,
"Mr. Vidal, your treatment is ready."
So I wonder in and take my treatment
and I hear this voice saying,
"Are you always running late?"
When they sorted out
what was going on,
they found out that I was having
Gore Vidal's enema.
[audience laughing]
Essentially, knowing your body is having
the feel of the balance of your body.
Bring your legs up.
Get them out straight.
[audience clapping]
Pull them in. Out.
One leg out and here we go again.
- How old are you?
- Fifty-five.
- What a body.
♪ [music] ♪
- In Bond Street before we came over--
I mean, after hours,
some of those boys
would come downstairs.
You know you have Peter O'Toole
who will drop in for haircut, you know.
When Roman Polanski was in town,
he'd come in for a haircut.
- Polanski was doing a movie in London
with this Catherine Deneuve.
[drumbeat]
Roman said, "I'd want to use
the balcony of your salon."
He said,
"I just need it for the weekend."
Well he stayed five days.
The clients loved it.
There was Catherine Deneuve,
being filmed on the balcony.
We were working down here
with our clients.
And of course it was exciting.
They found it fascinating.
And I guess he thought he owed me one,
'cause about six months later,
he called me and said,
"Hey, would you like to come do
Mia Farrow's hair for Rosemary's Baby?"
♪ [lullabye playing] ♪
It was quite a scene that whole haircut.
Paramount lot, stage 13,
they've put up a boxing ring.
I lead her from her dressing room
to the boxing ring.
♪ [music] ♪
Before we knew what was happening,
I was cutting her hair.
The press crawling to the boxing ring.
There was one guy under the chair
photographing us.
They were all over the place.
Roman was in there suddenly Mia
looks at the press, and says,
"What are you all doing here
photographing a hair cut?"
While the indigenous American
was suffering,
this sort of political thing
was going on. [chuckling]
I'm cutting her hair, I said,
"This is absolutely crazy."
It went into the movie.
- My god!
- It's Vidal Sassoon, It's very in.
- What's wrong with you?
- Do I look that bad?
- It's terrible!
- It was nutty, absolutely nutty.
But It was Hollywood. [chuckles]
There was no question about it.
It would not have happened that way
anywhere else.
I guess what it did, it brought the name
to middle America.
But it was always, can I improve on it
or what am I gonna do next.
I'm immediately attracted and fascinated
by marvelous hair
and the people that wear it. [chuckles]
We call it Sassooning.
Am Vidal Sassoon.
And if you don't look good,
we don't look good.
-Vidal said, "I wanna figure out
a way to earn a living..."
"while other people are sleeping."
The obvious was products.
♪ [music] ♪
- Quite simply we feel there are
four steps to beautiful hair.
- I met a man called Don Sullivan
and we talked about developing
a product company.
Talking simple, talking differently.
I was as excited about the packaging
as I was about the products.
-But it changed an industry.
His way of working
and his way of thinking.
- If we think of all these hairdressers
who will bring products today
they have to remember
that he was really the first.
You know, he had this worldwide-billion
dollar product enterprise
which, again in itself
is very far seeing.
♪ [music] ♪
- [Vidal] The salons were growing.
The schools were growing.
England was growing.
Europe was growing.
Our biggest success
was in Japan, China.
They loved it.
They absolutely loved it.
♪ [music] ♪
♪ It's really great to look your best ♪
♪ More beautiful each day ♪
♪ With silky, sexy, shiny hair ♪
♪ The Vidal Sasson way. ♪
♪ Because if you don't look good,
we don't look good.. ♪
♪ We take pride in you ♪
♪ If you don't look good,
we don't look good.. ♪
♪ Vidal Sassoon ♪
- [Beverly Sassoon] It seems like
it happened overnight but it didn't.
It took so long to get
the products off the ground
and to build the company.
We eventually moved
from New York to California
and we thought maybe it would be
an easier lifestyle for the kids.
I was concerned about it
because I grew up here.
And I have seen a lot of marriages
go under, and I don't know,
you can't blame Los Angeles
but I had a fear.
♪ [music] ♪
- [Vidal] Went very swimmingly
for a while.
We were doing things that
were quite extraordinary.
I mean, we had the best selling book,
For Your Beauty and Health.
It was number three in the country,
the book.
It was one of the first of its kind.
Beverly was terrific with yoga and these
marvelous pictures of her doing yoga.
'Cause I was always into exercise,
We were very much into the foods
that kept us healthy.
And our lifestyle,
we portray that in our book.
People seem to like it.
People wanted to buy it.
It actually sold 300,000 copies
in the first year,
and in 18 months
400,000 copies were sold.
Pretty extraordinary for a health book.
- They're gonna co-host a whole show
in beauty and health today.
Here are two people whose life together
makes them truly beautiful people,
Vidal and Beverly Sassoon.
Welcome them please.
[audience clapping and shouting]
- She was excellent on television.
When we worked the country with book,
she was pretty terrific.
She really knew her stuff.
- [Beverly] There was this television
station that was putting together
a week of TV programming
and every night,
they would have a different couple.
♪ [music playing] ♪
-Wednesday is Vidal Sassoon
and Beverly Sassoon.
Your host tonight on the
Monday to Friday show.
[audience clapping]
- This is --
- Good evening.
- This is gonna be a fun evening
I have a great feeling about it.
- Go ahead--you have something...
-What do you think folks?
This is George Hamilton's pajamas.
- Ha ha ha!
[audience laughing and clapping]
- We enjoyed it. We did many, many
episodes. It was very successful.
♪ Your new day, it's your new day...♪
-I was offered a show.
I did two hundred of them.
With some marvelous guests.
- Here he is the host of Your New Day,
Vidal Sassoon.
- What's your question?
- Ah, what's the price of a
Vidal Sassoon hairstyle?
- A Vidal Sassoon...Vi...
- I wanted to ask.
[audience laughing]
- Jumping and keeping it safe.
- You know I wouldn't miss an opportunity
to test this one out here.
Here it goes.
[jumping rope]
[audience clapping]
- I was having a ball except
I was neglecting what I had started.
The products were going but there was
no one out there promoting them.
And I had to make a big decision
after two hundred shows.
I couldn't, couldn't desert my own company
♪ [music] ♪
- Thank you Vidal.
- You've changed Vidal.
- Because you're using more
styling products
it's harder to get your hair
really clean and sexy.
New advanced salon formula.
- [unison] Thank you Vidal.
- If you don't look good,
we don't look good.
- I think the move from New York to L.A
was very good for products,
but it wasn't a very good move
family wise.
[audience clapping]
- And for today at the red section,
International Style-setter,
there he is Mr. Vidal Sassoon,
and his wife Beverly Sassoon.
- I think it suddenly struck her.
The lack of her own identity.
It all became a wee bit too much
for her emotionally.
- [Beverly] I'm pretty much
non-confrontational. I don't like it.
If I had learned that then,
I would have been able to maybe deal
with some of Vidal's behavior
and some of the -- well I perceived
to be as anger directed towards me.
But that's eventually what drove me away.
- I think one of the most difficult period
for me personally was the divorce.
We have three children in New York,
adopted David in Los Angeles.
*Adopting David -- he was three years old,
I think my past had something
to do with that.
Growing up in an orphanage,
it would be nice wouldn't it
if you took a young child
joined with our family.
The divorce really affected me
and affected my judgment.
Iv'e made decisions I may not have made
had I not been in the state
of that I was in at that time.
Because had I had it all to do again,
I would have not been seduced
to sell the product company.
♪ [music] ♪
- [Gordon] Vidal was absolutely
the creator
of the celebrity-endorsed
hair product line.
He did not intend for it to go mess
but it did very quickly.
It was in such demand
that it was uncontrollable.
So, he went it rather than against it.
He couldn't fight it.
- Then a company came along.
I am not mentioning names here.
But a company came along --
Richardson Vicks it was actually.
And with all kinds of promises about,
we're going international.
You are our only line and we'll take over.
So, you know, go out and do shows
in different countries and...
they really warmed me up.
And we went with Richardson-Vicks.
Of course about a year and a half later,
they sold out to Proctor and Gamble.
So all their fancy stories were at an end.
♪ [violin playing] ♪
You can't go through life.
You cannot, it's impossible
to go through life on a fairy tale.
Something that just happens
and it's so marvelous,
it's so marvelous, thus, the downs come
and you've got to still yourself.
♪ [music] ♪
Uhm, I think -- I know actually
because it happened again
this New Year's -- I'll never enjoy
a New Year's Day.
I'll walk away and get lost somewhere
and come back on January the 2nd.
Five years ago, New Years Eve,
my daughter Catya, my eldest girl,
who I absolutely adored and she was
very special to me -- she OD'd,
and it was the worst moment.
They called me New Years Day and said
she passed away that night, before the...
Many parents have gone through this
and they know the feeling.
[whirring]
It's a hard one to work through, you know.
♪ [music] ♪
- [Gordon] I think that you're beginning
to see the haircuts again.
We've had ten to twelve years
of long, long, long hair.
It doesn't look good on everyone.
Sassoon knew that.
People realize that there are really
fabulous shape
makes them look and feel great
and is very easy to take care of.
So, I think, it is in fact very modern,
it's about design.
Sassoon's effect was so far ranging
the geometry of it that you would probably
would have said, it was in fact
the iPod of its day;
It was the Apple --
it was design, design, design.
♪ [music] ♪
- Every single hairdresser
owes that guy something.
It's not just the geometric haircut
that we have to thank him for
it's today's hairdressing that we have
to thank him for.
- Vidal Sassoon is kind of a blueprint to
me of some sort of modern hairdressing.
So the images that I saw when I walked
into the salon the first time.
The pictures on the wall still are a part
of my sort of library.
- He's revolutionized
not just hair but fashion.
- I think it's recognized how important
Vidal has been to fashion history
that in itself
the influence of that fashion
and that whole persona with the hairdo
and the makeup had a huge influence
on architecture design in general
furniture, films, our whole visual world.
And here was a hairdresser who has done
something incredibly important.
- You know those hairstyles are as iconic
as they are because they live on.
How amazing that it's relevant now
as they were when they were created.
- This started a revolution
and that led into
the real revolution
which was letting hair be.
Even every straight bob is done
in the spirit of Sassoon.
-In all the countries, they wanted to know
about Vidal Sassoon
in terms of their hair now.
They felt completely comfortable
with that over-the-top Peggy Moffitt
thing that is so Vidal.
But they think of it as very now.
They don't, they don't look back.
- The shapes can come and go
but what he did to women,
the way he probably liberated women
is like something that is
bigger than just being a hairdresser.
- Oh wow!
[chuckling]
[people applauding]
- Hi, you look lovely, all of you.
- Thank you.
- It's a great haircut.
Yeah it looks fantastic.
- Lovely. Shake it.
- Shake it.
- He has the most incredible
political conscience
of anyone that I've known.
He loves the idea of
generosity in the community.
giving something back.
- We're involved in something
truly exciting in New Orleans.
I think the soul of America is at risk.
There are so many areas
where greed has taken over,
where mistakes have been made.
What's happening in New Orleans
is a total disregard
for the fundamental human instincts.
Two hundred and seventy-five
thousand people wiped out.
No homes, underwater. Wiped out.
The government that says we're not in the
real estate business, what an outrage.
I became so angered at this!
I said, "Look, let's get the hairdressing
craft behind this."
- Well he's given so much
to the hairstylists of the world
that Hairdressers Unlocking Hope
was a way for them to support him.
And with their help, he was
able to build 23 houses.
-This is not charity. This is the feeling
for our fellow citizens who are in need.
- Philanthropy from
an individual point of view
I think it is absolutely essential.
It also gives you a spiritual awareness
that I can't get from religions anymore.
- Now if you've read Vidal's life,
it would read as if it was quite tough.
He took what was presented
and used it to motivate himself.
Absolutely, he was determined
to be great at something.
So that is part of his legacy as well.
That you can in fact,
grow up in tough times.
You can create a path
that hasn't been created.
You can do something new
in any field and you can help people.
- He does ask, sometimes if I think
that he is a good person.
"Do you think I'm a good person?"
And I've often thought
that comes from his childhood
because I know that children
blame themselves
when their parents separate.
And they tend to blame themselves
for everything that happens to them
when they're little.
And I think somewhere inside of him, he
blamed himself for his parents' divorce.
And he even thought that he had to go
to the orphanage
because he was a bad boy.
And am not sure that he has ever
completely gotten over that.
- I met Ronnie, actually I was 62.
[chuckling]
And she was delightful 30 something.
Something about her that even
hard to describe.
There's a fascination,
been fascinated ever since.
Before I met Ronnie,
I'd finished with women.
To be with a woman permanently,
that was never gonna happen.
I was far more focused
on my kids, my work.
She came along and my life changed.
- Now his empire stretches across
the globe but what about the romance?
Well there's been plenty of that
throughout his glamorous career
but it's only with his present wife,
Ronnie,
that he believes
he's finally found the one.
- Ronnie because of a very good mind
and then a fascination for new things
has made my life
so much more interesting
there is no question about that.
- I've made him and his family a home
and he's expanded my horizons
He's shown me more of the world
and he's shown me what one individual
can do for the world.
♪ [music] ♪
- [Vidal] What have you got there?
- [Gordon] This is the book.
[chuckling]
- The book?
- This is essentially your life form
on the wall.
- I don't know if I want to see it.
[laughing]
- We've lived it
so you might as well relive it.
- [Vidal] Wow!
-[Gordon] It's pretty impressive isn't it?
- [Vidal] Yeah. Really yeah is.
♪ [music] ♪
- [Gordon] You get to a certain point
in your life and aware
that each day is a special day
'cause you understand
there are less of them to come.
And I think he's very, very aware of that.
♪ [music] ♪
[television audio]
- [Vidal] They haven't beaten Italy
for 88 years.
So this is extraordinary if they do it.
Yes! They got it. I'm pleased because
they deserve it.
How fortuitous to be able
to touch the human frame.
To be exhilarated by a craft
that constantly changes
To hold that such has grown
from the human form
that molds, creates, spontaneous fashion.
To be involved in the poetry of change,
that was the '60s.
So, from my point of view,
if you bring back the spirit.
That sense of purpose
and the wins of the '60s,
we'd will be much better off.
- [Announcer] Ladies and gentlemen,
Mr. Vidal Sassoon.
[crowd applause and cheering]
- You know I'm sitting here reflecting.
Really I'm wondering
how did it all happen?
How did so much adventure happen.
Going back all those years,
you think the excitement,
the creativity, the people you've met.
The extraordinary sense
of loneliness at times.
Most of my progressive thoughts
in work and attitude I've been alone.
I can remember one New Year
at the lyceum that was big,
it was a dance hall.
I was upstairs watching from the balcony,
all the revelers enjoying themselves.
I was looking down on maybe
a thousand or more people.
I didn't feel part of the crowd.
In my own loneliness, there was always
this sense that I wanted to be a winner.
But in the final analysis,
when all that's been said,
My heart was in hair.
Always has been, still is.
You know tomorrow is gonna be a day
that has never ever happened to me before.
Actually going to the Palace
to see the CB from the Queen.
The more I think about it, the more I
sense that it truly belongs to the craft.
It truly belongs to all those people
that helped me so much
in the development of our craft.
♪ [music] ♪
- I laugh and say to myself,
"God, I wish I had
the second original idea."
I would love to see some young person
on enormous energy,
create something new,
create something different.
When everybody tells you,
the doubters tell you,
"It can't be done" you know,
"You'd go broke."
or "All kinds of tragedies will come
your way." Nonsense.
If you can get to the root of who you are
the God of who you are
and make something happen from it --
in whatever field.
My sense is
you're gonna surprise yourself.
♪ [music] ♪